# Henrick Deschamps

Ph.D. candidate, Eng. in Computer Science and Network · Critical Distributed Systems Specialist

29 chemin Pouciquot, 31520, Ramonville Saint Agne, FRANCE

🛘 +33 (0) 664 1994 94 | 💆 contact@hnrck.io | 🦱 www.hnrck.io | 🖸 hnrck | 🛅 henrick-deschamps | 😘 henrick.deschamps

Seeking a challenging, responsible position as a distributed systems engineer in an agile aerospace structure with the objective of becoming an industrial expert.



# Summary \_\_\_\_\_

I am a French computer science and network engineer, and Ph.D. student at the ISAE-Supaero. I am Interested in critical real-time distributed systems.

Distributed systems are nowadays inevitable in the field of engineering, no system lives alone isolated from its environment, even among systems that were historically considered monolithic, which raises questions about resource sharing, reliability, and data partitioning.

Although each problem requires a customized solution, my preferred approach consists in respecting the partitions and dividing a system into components that can be interconnected by a framework, whatever the scale of this interconnection, from embedded networks to international distribution. Such an approach makes it possible to apply good industrial software practices while addressing emerging problems from networks and system states.

I have experienced this modular approach in software and systems, and I had the opportunity to develop it on the simulation of cyber-physical systems that can integrate humans, software and hardware.

## Skills

Programming C/C++, Python, Java, Haskell, Bash, Ada, LaTeX

Office softwares Word processor, spreadsheet, database, scientific writing

Software design UML, SysML, AADL, static code analysis, code instrumentation

**Devops** Versioning, virtualization, test automation, continuous integration

Frameworks and libraries STL, HLA (CERTI), MQTT, MPI, OpenMP, POSIX, Linux kernel, Qt5, nl

Tools CMake, Make, clang (-format, -tidy), debbuger, valgrind, wireshark, TCP tools, coverage, afl

Languages French, English, Chinese

# Work Experience\_\_\_\_

#### Airbus, Aircraft simulation department

Toulouse, France

Software Engineer for simulation architecture, Ph.D. Candidate

Mar. 2016 - Mar. 2019

- Formalization of the execution of a distributed simulation for the a priori validation of a simulation scheduling respecting aerospatial-specific constraints.
- Analyzis of simulation packages and frameworks for formalizing the logical components and the distributed execution architecture.
- Analyzis of existing simulations and technical documentations for formalizing of aerospatial-specific distributed simulation constraints.
- ullet Implementation of RROSACE a simple flight controller case study from ROSACE, in Matlab and C.
- Implementation of sEaplanes a simulation framework in C++ based on HLA, a publish-subscribe-based data exchange standard, with Ot interface.
- Implementation of a modulable and extensible allocation tool in Python, with multiple heuristics.

#### ISAE-Supaero (Superior Institute of Aeronautics and Space)

Toulouse, France

ATER (Temporary Teaching and Research Assistant)

Mar. 2016 - current

• Teaching assistant in C, Java, Real-time systems, SysML, and numerical analysis.

# Viveris Technologies

Toulouse, France

Software Engineer consultant for satellite ground segment communications

Dec. 2014 - Feb. 2016

- Implementation of a DVB-RCS2 communication protocol in satellite communications ground segment for Thalès Alenia Space.
- Development and integration of network modules in multi-threaded telecommunication kernel device. Open-source library available at hnrck/librle.
- Development of Quality of Service library for the satellite simulation environment, based on the libns.
- Development of test tools for continuous integration in Python, Ruby and Perl.
- Analysis of network packet scheduling for QoS validation.

Toulouse, France

Software Engineer Final year project

Feb. 2014 - Aug. 2016

- Internship in the modeling of avionic ethernet network QoS for validation of the quality of service rules.
- OmNet++/OmNest development of network scheduler models (C++ and NED languages).
- Minor bugs found in the OmNet++/OmNest inet library, one correction proposed and merged in the original library: inet-framework/inet/pull/18.
- Implementation of analysis tools in Python and Excel macro.

#### LAAS (Laboratory for Analysis and Architecture of Systems)

Toulouse, France

Software Engineer 4<sup>th</sup> year internship

Jun. 2013 - Aug. 2013

- M2M energy efficient communication. Software defined radios for wireless sensors network, with consideration for home automation and avionics applications.
- Manipulation of SDRs (Etus B 100/Etus N 100) and SDR software (GNURadio, Minicom, Iris, and LabView).
- Development of physical and mac layers for sensors network.

# Education \_\_\_\_

#### ISAE-Supaero (Superior Institute of Aeronautics and Space)

Toulouse, France

2016 - (expected) 2019

- Industrial Ph.D. in Networks, Telecoms, Systems and Architecture
- Ph.D. thesis entitled Scheduling of a cyber-physical system simulation.
- Supervised by Prs. Pierre Siron and Janette Cardoso.
- Co-supervised by Airbus through a CIFRE (Industrial Agreement of Training through Research).

#### INSA (National Institute of Applied Sciences)

Toulouse, France

Engineering Degree in Computer Science and Communication Networks

2009 - 2014

- Engineering school part of French Group A, delivering engineering degrees (master's level, 5 years of study), recognized by the French Engineering Title Conferment Commission, with international equivalence
- Computer Science, Modelling and Communication background.
- Specialization in Computer Science and Telecommunication Networks.
- Major in Communicative Distributed Systems, minor in IT Security.
- Student Clubs President and Secretary.

#### UQO (Quebec University in Ottawa)

Ottawa, Canada

Exchange student, Master in Computer Engineering, Telecommunication Networks and IT security

2013

- Exchange semester administered by the CREPUQ (Conference of Rectors and Principals of Québec Universities).
- GPA 4.3 / 4.3, A+ grade

#### Jules Renard Highschool

Nevers, France

French scientifical  ${\it Baccalaureat}$ 

2008

• With honours.

# Honors & Awards\_\_\_\_\_

Domestic

2014 **High-performing intern**, Airbus Group Innovation

Toulouse, France

#### Publications.

### Implementation of a Cyber-Physical System simulation components allocation tool

Ghent, Belgium
Oct. 2018

32<sup>nd</sup> European Simulation and Modelling Conf. - ESM'2018

## Coincidence Problem in CPS Simulations: the R-ROSACE Case Study

Proceedings of the 9<sup>th</sup> European Congress Embedded Real Time Software and Systems ERTS<sup>2</sup> 2018

Jan. 2018

Toulouse, France

#### Distributing Cyber-Physical Systems Simulation: The Satellite Constellation Case

 $\mathbf{5}^{\text{th}}$  Federated and Fractionated Satellite Systems Workshop

Toulouse, France
Nov. 2017

#### Toward a formalism to study the scheduling of cyber-physical systems simulations

2017 IEEE/ACM 21<sup>st</sup> International Symposium on Distributed Simulation and Real Time Applications (DS-RT)

Rome, Italy
Oct. 2017

May 7, 2019 Henrick Deschamps · Résumé 2/2